I see you.
I'm not sure.
I need to see if I can get my glasses.
Ice cream, cream.
I was trying to get my phone.
You know what makes it interesting is
she had water. You don't take care of
her.
Good morning, everybody.
Check, check, 1 2. Let's check the
battery.
Yeah, it should be good.
All right. How do we manage to start
exactly at
Okay.
The usual stuff. Please shut your
laptops.
The attendance poll is number 866.
And uh
Yeah.
This is our final week.
The last of two lect- the last two
lectures.
And uh then
we are done with most of the course,
except your videos, right?
Don't forget uh that all of you are
expected to judge
projects.
And we need you because that's the only
way we're going to get a proper peer
review of projects. Each project ends up
being reviewed by about
uh 10 to 15 of you guys, so that the any
word that we get as statistically
meaningful.
And of course, uh four or five of the
staff again to make sure that
the judgment is fair. So,
we need you to participate.
Anyway, uh
today's lecture this week's lecture is
on a topic that actually won a couple of
people a Nobel Prize in 20 2024.
Uh
the two Nobel laureates in physics in
physics in 2024
were Geoffrey
and John Hopfield. So,
today's lecture is what John Hopfield
brought to the world.
And Wednesday's lecture
will be Geoffrey Hinton Hinton's
extension of John Hopfield's network.
Which of course won both of them that
that that was what
kick-started the entire deep learning
revolution back in the '80s.
And it has continued till today, right?
So, here's where we begin.
These are the kinds of networks we have
seen so far, the one on the top right.
These are feedforward networks.
When you pass when you start up provided
with some information, the network keeps
processing it in a directional manner
until the information arrives at the
output, at which point the network
generates an output.
But what if
I could actually feed the output of the
network back into the input?
Now this becomes a loopy network.
Anytime you give the network an input,
it's not going to stop processing
because the output keeps going back in,
right? Does this remind you of
something?
Mhm.
Recurrent neural networks. This is much
like a recurrent neural network with uh
you know, variable length recurrent
recurrence, right? So, do you mind
turning your laptop please?
Yeah.
So, that's the kind of network we're
going to look at.
Loopy networks.
And specifically we're going to look at
a kind of the network which a network
which has a threshold activation. The
output is either a one or a minus one.
And so every neuron because it's loopy,
every neuron receives input from every
other neuron.
And every neuron's output also goes to
every other neuron.
Also, we're going to make these networks
symmetric because some of the math works
out for symmetric weight matrices.
Which means the because the information
from neuron A goes to neuron B, but the
information from the output of neuron B
also goes back to neuron A. There's a
connection between neuron A and neuron
B, and a different connection between
neuron B and neuron A, right?
They both have weights. They don't need
to have separate weights. So, we're
going to make the weights identical,
which means W I J equals W J I.
And this
is what we'll call a Hopfield network.
A network of neurons
where each neuron has a threshold
activation.
Every neuron's output goes to every
other neuron.
And the weights are symmetric. The
weight with which neuron I connects to
neuron J is the same as the weight with
which neuron J connects to neuron I.
Now, how does
such a network operate? Now, I could ask
you this question.
And at this point, you guys, having been
through the entire course, are uh
sufficiently knowledgeable, supposedly,
that I can hand this clicker to you, and
you can come here and do the rest of the
lecture.
Any volunteers?
Right. How would such a network behave?
Anybody?
How would such a network behave?
I'll give you 5 seconds, and then I'll
give you the answer.
Anyone? Anyone on Zoom?
No responses? Okay, here's what happens,
right?
At each time, the neuron receives what I
will call a field, which is the affine
term. Remember how these neurons
operate? First, you compute an affine
function of the outputs of of all of its
inputs.
So, this I'm going to call a field.
Now, if it has a threshold activation,
now, if the
uh neuron is you know, the output of the
neuron is going to become one if the
field is positive,
it's going to become a minus one if the
field is negative.
But, here's a different way of thinking
about it.
If the output of the neuron is currently
positive, and the field is negative,
what happens to the output?
Does it stay the same or does it flip?
It flips, right? If the output is
positive and the field is positive, what
happens?
>> It stays the
>> Stays the same, right? So also, if the
output is negative and the field is
negative,
stays the same. But if the signs are
different,
>> They change.
>> They change. So the situation is that
anytime the sign of the field opposes
the sign of the output of the neuron,
that neuron neuron flips. So
you can say the simple way of stating it
is Y goes to minus Y
if
the sign of the output of the neuron and
the field are not the same, which is the
same as saying if you take the product
of the output of the neuron
and the field at the neuron, if both of
them have the same sign, the product is
going to be positive, otherwise it's
going to be negative. So if this product
is positive, the output of the neuron
doesn't change. If the product is
negative, the neuron
flips, right?
So
a neuron flips if the weighted sum of
other neurons' outputs is of the
opposite sign to its own current output
value.
But when this happens, this new this
network is loopy, right?
If this neuron flips, what happens at
the other neurons?
Do their fields stay the same or do they
change?
Come on, guys.
>> They're They're going to change. They're
going to change.
>> They're going to change, right? Because
this neuron's output has changed, so its
contribution to the field at all the
other neurons has changed.
Which means those fields could change.
Some of them could change sign because
of this one, right? And so you'd have a
situation like this. Let's say this is
how you started off. This is a loopy
network.
So you're going to initialize the
network at some at some state. You're
going to assign a current output value
because the outputs and inputs are the
same, right? So you're going to
currently assign a current output value
to all of the neurons. They have their
weights.
And then every neuron is going to check
its output against its field, and some
neuron is going to find that its field
does not match its current output. It's
going to flip its value.
But when this happens,
the fields at other neurons are going to
change. Some other neuron is going to
flip.
And when that happens, the fields at
other neurons are going to change.
And neurons are going to flip. The
neuron that flip flipped might be a
neuron that flipped earlier because now,
thanks to its own the change in its own
output, the fields at all the other
neurons changed. So, those neurons
changed, which means the field at the
neuron has now changed all over again.
And so, the neuron
may flip, right?
And so, if the sign of the field at any
neuron opposes its own sign, it flips to
match the field,
which will change the field at other
nodes, which may then flip,
which may cause other neurons, including
the first one, to flip.
And this thing can go on forever. This
makes sense to all of you.
And this is an outcome of the network
being
what?
Hm?
Loopy, right? Because the output is
going back to the input. Anytime a
neuron's output changes, it's going to
change the outputs of other neurons. But
anytime the outputs of the other neurons
change, the input to this neuron has
changed. This neuron could also change
its output and then trigger the whole
thing up all over again. And so, here is
a loopy network. I just randomly created
it. 20 evolutions of the network. You
can you can see how this flips, right?
Things begin flipping all over the
place.
20 iterations is kind of slow, not
enough to see what's happening.
So, I gave you 20 evolutions, right? Red
is one.
Yellow is minus one.
And you can see what's happening. It
just keeps flipping back and forth back
and forth back and forth.
Does this make sense to all of you?
Right. Yes, no?
Okay, one last one you know one last
week guys. Everybody say yes together.
1 2 3
>> Yes.
>> Thank you, right? And so
how long do you think this will
continue?
Forever? How many of you think this
could continue forever?
And how many of you think there's a
natural reason for it to stop at some
point?
Obviously it's a trick question. When I
give you that question, it means the
answer is yes to the second one, right?
And there's a way of proving this.
Let's see how, right?
Will this behavior continue forever? The
answer is no.
So, consider any particular neuron. Do
we have a chalk?
I'm sure there are chalks here.
Okay.
Proof that this semester is over, the
chalks are all gone.
Huh.
Okay.
In the bag?
>> Ah, no. I have some.
>> So, here's what happens at any neuron.
Let's say
this
is the time T
at which the neuron responds to what has
happened to its input, right? So,
there's a field out here.
And so, let me call the output Y minus.
And there's a field value at the neuron,
right?
And there's a Y plus.
After it has responded, the field hasn't
changed. It's just that particular
neuron has you know, at that instant the
neuron has flipped, not right?
Now,
let's say
Y minus times F
is positive.
Then what's is y+? What's the
relationship between y+ and y- in this
case?
>> They're the same.
>> They are the same, right?
So,
so
what is y+f - y-f
in this case?
What's it going to be?
Hm?
>> Zero.
>> Zero, because y+ and y- are the same,
right?
It's going to be zero.
Okay, what if
y-f
is less than zero? Then what happens?
What happens?
If the product of the output of the
neuron and the field is negative, what
does it mean? Are the two matched in
sign?
So, what will happen to the output of
the neuron?
>> It's negative. It's negative.
>> It's going to
flip, correct?
So, you're going to say y+
equals minus of
y-. Is everybody with me?
Right? Implies
y+f
- y-f
is going to be
two times
y
+ f.
Right?
Yes or no?
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
And so,
every every time a new if a neuron
doesn't flip,
this product
nothing happens to it. It stays
constant.
Every time a neuron flips,
that product is going to increase in
value
because the product of the output of the
neuron and the field
that actually changed
when the neuron flipped. It always
increased, right?
That makes sense to all of you guys?
Right. If you look at this product,
the term I'm interested in is Y * F.
When Y * F So, when Y * F was positive,
it didn't change
after the flip.
When Y * F was negative, it changed.
And so, as a result of the change, the
thing value actually increased by
2 * Y plus, right? Times F to a positive
value.
That makes sense to everybody?
Now, how much will it change by? Is it
Is this change unbounded or is there an
upper limit to how much it can change
by?
Anyone? How much can it change by?
Hm?
A thought?
So, let's just take a look at this guy,
right? That's this term here.
I've just written it out and I've summed
this over all the neurons.
The output of the the product of the
field and the output of the neuron.
This guy
is simply going to be the sum of
because the field is given as a sum over
all pairs of neurons of W I J * Y I Y J
plus
B I * Y I. I mean, that equation makes
sense to everybody?
Now, anytime you
a neuron flips, this thing is going to
increase at that neuron. So, anytime the
overall the network evolves, it's going
to increase by some amount, right?
And so,
at any given neuron, this value is going
to increase by Y 2 * Y plus * W I J
Y I Y J plus B Y, right?
Now, these
Y is either plus one or minus one.
Right?
Both of these Ys are either plus one or
minus one.
So, the So, if you want to take the best
case value, both of them are plus one.
Right?
This is bounded by summation of the all
the weights
and biases, the sum of all the fields.
Correct? So, in other words,
anytime
the neuron evolves,
the smallest uh this guy is going to
increment.
The change in the
field has a
s- minimum value.
There's at least a um a minimum number
There's There's a minimum amount by
which this thing is going to change
at the least, anytime the neuron
the network evolves.
Because all the Ws and Bs are bounded.
The Ws don't go to zero.
They have a finite value. Right? If all
the Ws went to zero, you have no network
at all. And the Bs, even if all the Bs
went to zero, there's a there's a
minimum amount. So, you're basically
summing at each neuron
the
This is just, you know, the all the
incoming weights and the bias.
That's the smallest amount by which the
uh
Where did I put the chalk?
This thing is going to increase. So, if
you consider this one,
since the Ys are always one or minus
one,
two times F
is the is is how much it changes by. The
field is finite at every neuron.
Otherwise, the neuron's not part of the
network at all. So, the smallest field
is how much
the D value changes by.
But, the D is also upper bounded, right?
Okay, but first, here are
Okay, hang on. But, D is also
upper-bounded.
The D is upper-bounded also by the sum
of the fields at all the neurons.
So, you have an upper-bounded value
and you have a lower bound on how much
it can increase by.
The number of steps, number of
increments till you get the upper bound,
is going to be the upper bound in the
value divided by the smallest increment.
This is finite.
Which means that this network is going
to stop evolving in a finite number of
steps. It's not going to run forever.
It's going to stop evolving in a finite
number of steps. Here's a problem.
Okay.
Time's up.
Someone want to answer the first
question?
What's the answer to the first question?
True. Second?
And the third?
False to How many of you think it's
true?
Okay. How many of you noticed that it's
a Hopfield network is a recurrent
network?
Right? Basically, anytime you have a
loop,
this looks like so.
It's an arbitrarily deep
recurrent network.
So, you have all the
neurons getting an initial value.
Then, all the neurons
are going to evolve based on the current
outputs.
Then all the neurons are going to evolve
again
based on the outputs over here. It's
basically the same network over and over
again. The distinction being these
weights are the same as these weights
are the same as these weights. So, it's
basically a recurrent network with an
input at time zero and no further
inputs, which is also an MLP
an arbitrarily deep MLP where every
layer is identical to every other layer.
Does that make sense everybody? Right.
Okay.
So, the story so far, a Hopfield network
is a loopy binary network with symmetric
connections.
Every neuron attempts to align itself
with the sign of the field at the
neuron.
Given an initial configuration, the
neurons in the network begin to flip to
align themselves in this manner.
And each evolve evolution of the network
is guaranteed
to decrease an energy, right? This D
value is
If you think of the negative of the D
value as an energy,
then just as the D value keeps
incrementing,
if you thought thought of the D the
negative of D as an energy, that keeps
decrementing and every evolution
decrements this energy by a finite
amount of finite amount.
Now, the gap between the D and the
energy term is on the slides. They kind
of hit, right? Anyways.
So, what is the energy of an a Hopfield
network?
I'm going to define the energy that
should have been a plus. I'm not sure
why
that became a minus. I'm sure I edited
it, right? So, you're going to define
the energy of the network as
minus half summation all over all the
neurons of YJ
field at J.
So, minus half.
Why the half?
Anytime we do again, anytime we do we
work on quadratic terms, we like to have
a half outside because it makes things
simpler when you differentiate.
So, there's an arithmetic reason for it,
but uh it also has to do with how we
actually define energies in a in a
slightly different context, which is uh
spin glasses.
Why did these guys win uh
uh Nobel Prizes in Physics? Because they
related the neural network to a very
physical process, spin glasses.
So, where did this energy concept
suddenly
sprout out of, right?
Ah,
I fixed the minus to a plus here, right?
So, where did the energy come out of?
Here's where.
Spin glasses, ferroelectric materials
where you have a bunch of magnetic
dipoles.
And so, if you have a bunch of magnetic
dipoles, the field at each at every
dipole you have a field.
Now, the field at any dipole is because
of all the other dipoles, because every
one of these dipoles is basically a
magnetic moment, right? So, they're
influencing the uh
the entire medium. So, I have a bunch of
dipoles.
D1, D2, D3, they just
organize any odd how. If you consider
this one location,
all of these dipoles are influence are
cause a field at this location.
The dipole itself has some orientation.
And I in the nature of all magnets, it's
going to try to align itself with the
field at that particular location.
But when it when it orients itself, it
might flip.
If it flips, it's going to change the
fields at all the other dipoles. It's a
classic this is spin glass, right? And
so, what is the field at any dipole?
The field at any dipole is going to be,
you know, let's say you have a
magnet out here. This magnet is going to
be
exerting an external field B.
And so, the field at any dipole is going
to be the sum of whatever comes from
here
plus the sum from what comes from all
the other dipoles.
And the influence of any particular
dipole over here depends on two factors,
the uh
the uh material itself,
the dielectric constant of the material,
and the distance,
the inverse distance. So the interaction
between a dipole I and a dipole J has
some term J written by the upper case J,
J J I.
And the B represents the external field.
And each dipole is going to try to align
itself with that field, right?
If the dipole is oriented
correctly for the field, it's going to
stay the same. If it's
orientation is off, it's going to flip.
And eventually the whole the whole
system is going to come to some kind of
an equilibrium, right?
So
if a dipole flips, it changes the
field at other dipoles.
And it may cause those dipoles to flip.
It may change which may change the field
at the current dipole.
And the whole thing can keep going on,
right? So how long will this go on?
When does it stop?
So you can think of
Now obviously magnetic materials have
the ability to do work. They have
potential. So they have uh uh we use
them for all kinds of for purposes. We
use them to run trains, right? So they
have the capacity to do work.
What is this? So how do you quantify
this potential energy? The energy at any
dipole is simply the product of its own
value and the field at the dipole.
Classic physics. If you've done physics
101, you know, the first class in
electromagnetics gave you this
information, right? And so
they uh field at any dipole is going to
be product the product of the dipole and
the the energy of any dipole is going to
be the product
of the dipole itself and the field at
the dipole are half half that much.
You sum this over all dipoles. That is
the energy of the entire
medium.
And then we know this about
about physical
media. When you just let them be,
they're going to keep evolving towards
lower energy
states, right? And when they do this,
what happens to the excess energy?
Anybody recall?
What happens to that?
It's released in some manner, right?
Heat, what have you.
We know this. You guys shouldn't be so
quiet.
This is your first year of
first first undergrad
physics course, which I'm sure everybody
here has taken, right?
And so,
the system is going to evolve to
minimize this energy,
and dipole stop flipping eventually at
some point you're going to get to a
state
where if any dipole flips, the energy is
going to increase, at which point the
dipoles will stop flipping. So, one way
to think about it is I mean,
it's a multi-dimensional thing. You'd
have a billion dipoles or a trillion
dipoles, and so, you know, I can't
really draw these things in a million
trillion dimensional space.
This is just for
visualization. If I laid all the states,
now what I call a state is the
set of orientations of all the dipoles.
That can be thought of as a vector,
right? A state.
And so, if I arranged all the states in
some topological manner, so,
uh
the adjacent points represent adjacent
states,
then if I thought of the energy of the
entire medium
as or this this term
as a variable that can be plotted
against state, that
plot is going to look something like
this.
There are some states where the energy
is small. Minor changes are going to
change increase the energy a little bit.
There are other states where the energy
is high.
Minor changes are likely going to
decrease the energy. So, this is the
energy contour.
And anytime you initialize the system in
any state, it's going to begin evolving
till it gets to a minimum energy state.
At which point it can't evolve anymore
because if it tries to evolve, the
energy is actually going to increase,
right? So, this is how the whole thing
behaves.
And so, this Hopfield network is
actually a computational analog to spin
glasses.
The equations are exactly the same.
Every neuron is the equivalent of a
dipole.
It receives a field which is a
combination of the B, the bias term,
which is the external magnetic field,
and the weighted sum of the outputs of
the other neurons, which is like the
effect of all the other dipoles in the
medium.
And so, this
- 1/2 summation I J W I J Y I Y J + B I
Y I. This is exactly analogous to the
energy of
a
spin glass.
And so, this system too is going to
evolve in exactly the same manner.
If you just laid all the states out,
then you are going to have an energy
contour,
and uh
like so, and the system is going to
evolve until the energy can no longer
decrease.
Right? You want to turn in the phone
upside down.
Thank you. Yes.
So, that's what we proved when you
before when you when you were late.
When you were late in class, we proved
that it's going to stop evolving, right?
When you were late to class.
So, the energy is upper bounded,
and the change in energy when when
something flips
is lower bounded. So, an upper bound
divided by divided by a finite lower I
mean, no.
Yeah,
a finite value is going to
result in a finite number of steps. So,
once you once you
evolve for a finite number of steps, no
more evolution is possible.
Okay? So, and the bias over here, that
is the external external magnetic field.
In my equations, I won't explicitly or
show the bias always because it's like
having an extra the
this bias can be thought of
as an extra dipole
whose value is always fixed, right? And
so, the equations I may not write it in
the equations.
And so, then I can just write the inner
energy as
minus half
summation over all pairs of neurons w i
j y i y j, okay?
And now
the network is going to evolve until it
arrives at a local manner in a minimum
in the energy contour, just like your
spin glass.
Right?
But, from a network perspective, this is
what we call a content addressable
memory.
Also called associative memory. Now, in
a standard memory, if you want to recall
a pattern, how do you recall it?
On your computer, if you want to recall
something, how do you recall it?
What is your standard technique? Come
on, guys, you know this. You're all
computer scientists.
What do you do if you want to recall
something? If you want to pull up
something from memory, what do you do?
Hm?
>> Open the history.
>> Pardon me?
>> Open the history? No, is that what you
do? If you're writing a program, what
would you do?
Uh-huh.
Yeah.
but it depends on the specific
problem
that I structure
I would like to do this.
>> But exactly how do you do it?
It's done by address, right? Every entry
that you have stored in memory has an
address.
And so if you want to recall you want to
recall something
you just say what is the memory location
the value at this location.
So if you got an array you can say
return the array array value at index
370.
If you got a data structure you know
here's a key return the value at
you know at this key. At the hardware
level what this means is that every cell
every register has an address a physical
address. You go to invoke that address
it's going to read stuff off of that
address.
What you recall is not related to how
you recall it, right? It doesn't matter
what is stored in the 77th location of
your array so long as you feed it 77
it's going to return that value.
So this is an address
addressed memory, right?
But there's a different way of doing it.
It's called content address memory. If
you want to recall something then you uh
enter
a partial value or a corrupted value of
it.
And then from this you try to recall
what the entire thing was. That's a lot
like how humans operate. You might be
you might remember that you know
uh
you might sort of
recall recall how do you yourself recall
things?
You start off with what it is you want
to recall, right? And you have some
vague idea of it. And then from that you
build up your entire memory. So it's not
from you know I'm going to go into this
cell in my brain. Here's a pattern let
me fill it out.
What do you think this guy is doing?
This guy is doing exactly the same
thing.
So, if I
uh let this network evolve, it's going
to evolve into a pattern. Which pattern
will it evolve into?
So, if you go if you consider this one
over here,
if I start off the ball at that location
and it evolves, it's going to fall into
that particular valley.
So, it's the closest
remembered pattern that is going to
evolve into. So, here is an example.
Uh these are content addressable
memories. Those two patterns to the
left, a neural network has been designed
to remember these two guys. What do you
mean by remember is that these two guys
are minimum energy
configurations for the network.
And so now if you initialize the network
with a slightly different configuration,
like say the degraded degraded version
of
of Bugs Bunny,
and you let then you let it evolve,
it's going to evolve into the entire
Bugs Bunny.
Or if you give it a partial copy of
Chip and Dale,
it's going to evolve to fill out the
entire pattern. So, again, you're not
remembering recalling based on where the
memory is,
you're recalling based on what is
supposed to be remembered.
This is content addressable memory. It's
a It's a major area of research.
Hopfield networks were one of the ways
to do it, right? So, here's a very nice
uh
dem- demo that some guy put up on the
web.
I don't know who it is. Whoever it is,
thank you. I stole it.
So, uh
he has uh stored some
patterns stored in the sense that he has
created a neural network
with weights such that these patterns
are minimum energy configurations.
And then when he
a penguin, the Joker, right?
And then he starts off with some random
initial value,
and then he lets it evolve, voila, it
comes back with a penguin. Start off
with a different random initial value.
And it recreates
this joker. He started off with
something that looked like the Earth.
But the Earth was not stored. So, when
he when it evolved
it pulled up the face, right, the joker,
and so on, right? So, is the concept of
a content addressable memory making
sense to you guys?
Right. What is the first question that
comes to mind in this case?
>> The main thing I want to push out of my
mind right now is like what about time
and space complexity compared to other
algorithms?
>> Forget about all of that, right?
If I want you to
build I want you to build me a network
that remembers
the penguin.
What is
>> Do you train it?
>> How do you train it, right? What do you
mean by training?
>> How do you get it to remember
or how do you get the uh
lowest energy state to be something
>> How How do you set the weights such that
the pattern you're trying to remember is
the lowest energy state, right? That's
the basic question.
So, first, how do I how do you let the
network evolve? Simple enough. You're
going to initialize the network with
some pattern.
And then at each neuron you're going to
compare
you're just going to apply a threshold
activation to the field at the neuron.
You can do this neuron by neuron or you
can do this
uh over the entire set of neurons all at
once.
So, this is the same as saying I'm going
to say Y if Y is
this if this entire thing is called Y
then I can say Y equals theta of
W times Y, right? You're just iterating
this
uh till convergence. And what What is
convergence? Convergence is when the
overall energy of the network no longer
reduces after an iteration. So, once
again, this is like an arbitrarily deep
MLP or a recurrent network
except that the number of steps you take
depends on the initial value. At some
point the output stops changing
and then
you stop computing.
Right?
So, this is and the energy of course I
can write this as Y equals theta times
theta of W Y and you stop doing this
when the energy which is defined as
minus point five
Y transpose W Y.
This is just a matrix notation to write
out the energy that that stops changing,
right? So,
a Hopfield network is a loopy binary
network with symmetric connections.
Neurons try to align themselves to the
local field.
Given an initial configuration, the
patterns will evolve until the energy of
the network achieves a local minimum.
The evolution will be monotonic
in total energy. The dynamics mimic
those of a spin glass.
And because it's quadratic, the energy
is quadratic,
if Y is a stable pattern, minus Y is
also a stable pattern.
Right? And
the network acts as a content
addressable memory. If you initialize
the network with a somewhat damaged
version of a local minimum pattern, it's
going to evolve into that pattern,
effectively recalling the pattern from a
damaged or incomplete version, right?
So,
Oh.
Okay.
All right.
Somebody on Zoom, you want to answer
this?
Someone on Zoom?
1 2 3 they said.
How many of you agree?
Which one's the right one? Okay.
All right.
So,
the network activations evolve until the
energy arrives at a local minimum.
They're a form of content-addressable
memory.
It's not possible
to look at the weights and determine
what the stored memories are. Can I see
the laptop, please?
That is there's nothing in the weights
that tells you exactly what pattern is
remembered.
And that's what makes the whole thing
challenging.
The reason for this is that there's a
there's a non-linear element, the
activation, the threshold activation. If
you got rid of the threshold activation,
then this is just, you know, finding the
eigenvectors of your weight matrix,
you're fine.
But,
once you put in a non-linearity, that
thing kind of breaks down.
So, the issue is how do you make the
network store a specific pattern or set
of patterns?
How many patterns can we store and how
do we retrieve a specific pattern?
At this point, it gets a little mathy,
but the math is not complex, right? But,
uh I'm going to skip most of the math.
Question is how do you teach a network
to remember this image?
Now, if the neuron has N pixels,
obviously there's one pixel per one
neuron per pixel, so the network is also
going to require
N neurons in it, right?
Every neuron connects to every other
neuron. The weights are symmetric.
Now, it's not mandatory for the weights
to be symmetric, but some of the
mathematical properties only hold for
symmetric matrices.
And so, uh
uh the uh
This means that the number of new
weights
is going to be W squared over two,
right? Minus W squared over two minus W
because a neuron doesn't connect to
itself.
And so
what we know is that memorized patterns
are stable energy states.
The energy contour is a function of W.
As you keep changing W
the energy changes.
And so you want to design the W such
that whatever pattern it is you you have
is a is a minimum.
And it's stable, right?
And they can you can actually have
multiple local minimum.
In your contour in your in your energy
contour. So this is for a given W. For a
given W you're going to have an energy
contour of this kind. And you as you can
see from this figure you can have
multiple local minima. Each of them is
going to be one one stored pattern.
And you want to design your W such that
all of these local minima are patterns
that you really want remember.
Now
this energy is quadratic, right?
How many minima does a quadratic have?
Okay.
But is this does this have this
quadratic even have a minimum?
It's W.
If W is
What what is the condition on W for
there to be a global minimum?
For a quadratic.
The W is a second derivative, right?
If the second derivative is negative,
will it have a minimum?
No, right? The second derivative has to
be positive to have for it to have a
minimum, which means the way this thing
is set up the W's all of the eigen
values of of W are going to be negative.
It's going to be an inverted bowl.
Which means it doesn't matter where you
start
it's going to keep evolving until the
energy until you hit energy as
an energy of minus infinity, right?
So, why do I say there are
a finite number of local minima? This
has to do with the fact that we're using
a threshold activation.
When I use a threshold activation, then
the only values that I permit So, if you
know, if this is the energy contour,
this is what it's going to look like
from the top.
Series of ellipses. Again, it's a
quadratic.
But, the only configurations I permit
are the value ones where the Y values
are all plus one or minus one, the
corners of a hypercube.
And then you can see over here that not
all corners have the same energy. Some
corners have higher energy, some corners
have lower energy. Can somebody tell me
which corners have high energy and which
ones have low energy over here?
Anyone?
Just by looking at the figure?
Yeah. Demash?
>> I like the top
uh right and then the bottom left.
>> So, as you go out, the rings that are
farther out have lower energy.
Right? So, the corners that are on the
farthest rings have the lowest energy.
And so, these these two guys over here,
they are the ones with the lowest
energy.
And no matter where you start from, the
thing is going to keep evolving until it
falls into one of these patterns.
In my many uh my in high dimensions, you
can have any number of these guys.
And so, you want to design your weight
matrix such that the bowl has the shape
such that these guys
are minimum energy locations.
And if you try to escape from them, you
cannot.
Now, this means there are two
conditions, right? Uh there are two
different things.
When I'm start when I start off in some
pattern,
there
there are two reasons why the pattern
may not change.
The pattern may not The pattern may not
change. The pattern will not change if
the field at every location
matches the sign of the neuron.
This will happen
at a local maximum because the
derivative is
zero.
It's also going to happen at a minimum
because the derivative is zero, right?
So, what distinguishes the maxima and
the minima?
Anyone?
In terms of the Hopfield network?
How do you know if it's a maximum or a
minimum?
Yeah.
>> If you perturb it a little
>> If you perturb it a little bit, you're
going to go swinging wildly away from
the maximum.
At the minimum, you're going to go right
back, right? So, both maxima and minima
are stationary.
Only minima are stable.
If you want to remember something, you
want the patterns to be both stationary
and stable.
Make sense? Stationarity is a necessary,
but not sufficient condition. Stability
is both.
Okay.
And so, you can also have
if you design your network,
your network is will have minima at the
locations you want, but it's going to
have a bunch of other minima as well.
These other minima are what you call
false memories. It turns out that as
humans, we have these too.
In fact, they can be manipulated.
Uh
where you create entire methodologies in
your head based on things you know,
things you don't know, and things you
imagine.
And for you, these are solid memories.
It happens to every one of us. It
happens to Hopfield networks as well.
So,
when you want to store a pattern, you
want to design the weights such that the
energy is a local minimum at the desired
pattern.
If I want to store only one pattern, if
I've just got only one pattern to
remember,
then it's easy.
I want the sign of the field at every
neuron to be the same as the
neuron value itself. That's when the
energy when that's when the neuron will
not flip, right? This is what we want
for stationarity.
And so,
the simplest thing
we can do is Hebbian learning. How many
of you remember Hebbian learning? What
was Hebbian learning?
Guys?
Lecture one, you can't have forgotten by
lecture 24.
What was Hebbian learning?
Hm?
I kept telling you that Hebbian learning
is actually the learning rule that we
keep coming back to. Everything
eventually collapses to Hebbian
learning.
So, if I have two neurons
where
uh
I want the increase of one neuron to
have influence on on the other neuron in
a specific way. I want the weight to be
proportional to the product of the two
neurons. This is what Donald Donald Hebb
suggested way back in the day, right?
And this was the basic rule that we kept
modifying a little bit to give us the
perceptron learning rule, which gave us
the gradient descent algorithm. So, the
Hebbian learning rule says that if I
choose a specific pattern
to remember, then the weight of the two
neurons that connect those
of that connects two neurons
has simply got to be the product of the
two neurons themselves. So, w i j is
going to be just y i * y j.
And if you set it so, then it's very
easy to so show that this guy actually
actually gives you a network for which
that pattern is a
is is remembered.
How do you show this? Very simple. The w
i j is going to be y i y j. So, for at
any neuron, w i you know, the sum over
all this is the field. Sum over all j of
w j i * y i. But w j i simply is simply
y j * y i, right?
And so, y i
w j i * y j. So, this gives you YJ
squared.
You're not summing over YI, so the YI
comes out, right?
It's summation of YJ squared YI.
Summation over J. YJ squared is a
positive value.
So, it's YI times some positive value.
The sign of this is the same as YI
itself.
And so, you can see that this guy is
actually a stationary pattern. No neuron
is ever going to change its value if you
set the weights
according to the Hebbian learning rule.
We've shown stationarity. The other
requirement is stability. Stability is
to show that this has the lowest
possible energy, and that too is
possible to show.
Right? If I look at the energy
the energy is over over all neuron pairs
of
sum over all neuron pairs of WJI times
YI YJ, right? But, WJI is just YJ times
YI all over again.
So, this is simply the sum over all
neurons
of YI squared times YJ squared. YI and
YJ are both plus or minus one. When you
square them, that term inside the
summation is always one.
So, you're basically just summing
ones.
And that's just going to give you -0.5 *
n * n - 1. And it's very easy to show
that there's no arrangement of values
that's actually going to give you an
energy lower than this.
So, the energy of the target pattern is
the global minimum.
So, if I just use the Hebbian learning
rule, you end up with a network where
the target pattern is not only
stationary, it's actually the lower
minimum energy pattern. Any deviation
from this pattern is going to cause the
network to evolve
into this pattern. And so, this is a
perfect rule for remembering one
pattern.
What if you want to remember a
collection of patterns?
So, this was proposed by John
John Hopfield.
And Hopfield suggested, okay, this thing
stable.
Uh
here's actually a visualization of how
that goes, right?
So, this is a Karnaugh map. All of you
remember Karnaugh maps, I'm sure.
And here I'm trying to remember a
four-bit pattern.
And the specific four-bit pattern I'm
trying to remember is the one in yellow.
Now, if I set the energy according to
the Hebbian learning rule,
then I've just shown the energy at each
pattern by the color.
And you can see that the energy is
minimum at the target pattern. The
energy is also minimum at a second
pattern.
Why do I have a second pattern?
Anybody?
Why?
>> What?
Why is it still the same energy?
>> Yeah, if you just negate everything,
it's still the same energy. It's Y and
minus Y. Those are the the two stable
patterns. And you can see how this thing
evolves, right? So, if I set the network
to say this guy,
then this has higher energy than all its
neighbors, so it's going to move into
this one. This has higher energy than
this one, so it's going to move into
that pattern. So, it doesn't matter
where you begin, eventually it's going
to
evolve into one of the two yellow
squares, which is a pattern that you
want to remember, okay?
Now, if you want to store more than one
pattern,
Hopfield suggested that the way to do it
is to just compute an average of many
different
networks, each of which has been trained
using the
Hebbian rule.
So,
this means that the any particular
weight
is the sum average over all patterns
that you want to remember
of the product
of the bits on either side of the
weight.
So, for a for the target pattern.
Now, this is an obvious connection
obvious extension, right? If I have a
rule for one pattern, I can apply the
same rule to every one of the patterns I
want to remember and then average the
lot. It turns out it's not a very great
idea. If you do things in this manner,
then the maximum number of patterns that
you can remember is about 0.14 n
where n is the number of pixels and is a
in the picture or n is the number of
neurons in the network. So, if I have a
million
neuron network,
then I can
store at most
like 140,000, is it?
patterns.
Uh which is not a very great thing,
right? Now, if you think about an
address-based network, if I have a
million neuron network, I can remember
two raised to
1 million different patterns. I can
still remember pretty much anything I
want to remember because all I I'm
interested in is the address.
So, in terms of returns on investment,
this is really poor.
But, here's one way of doing it, right?
And even so,
uh the uh
these 0.14 n patterns are not all
perfectly remembered.
Some of them they're remembered in a
probabilistic sense. Some of them might
not be remembered at all, okay?
So,
here's where Hopfield left it off. You
can store up to 0.14 n random patterns
with a recall error of 0.4%. That's
0.004. Meaning meaning four out of 1,000
times, the pattern that you're trying to
remember won't actually be remembered.
It's going to be what you're going to
remember something else, right?
But, you also get an exchange parasitic
parasitic patterns. What I mean by
parasitic patterns are these memories
that you don't really want. They're not
actual memories, but somehow they end up
being
local minima in your energy contour and
your network remembers it, right?
So,
the fact of the matter is that the
network actually has a capacity to store
more than 0.14 n patterns. We have
examples on the slide showing you why
this is the case, lots of pictures.
But, there's also some very clean math
for this, which a whole bunch of people
worked on, right? So, again, what are
these parasitic patterns? If I remember
two patterns shown by the locations of
the blue lines, it turns out that if I'm
using the heavy-end rule,
any pattern which is a linear
combination of these two guys, or uh
uh an uh an average of these guys,
that too ends up having a minimum energy
configuration, only for heavy-end
learning.
And so, these things are bad.
You're remembering things that aren't
really true, right? You remember an
apple, you remember a tree, you also
remember something that's neither an
apple nor a tree, half an apple and half
a tree, right? You uh remember a
you know, donkey, you remember a horse,
you also remember a mule, though you
never saw one. Okay. So,
the uh capacity of a network,
I'm building a million neuron network.
How many things can I remember?
It turns out that if you use Hopfield's
method, you can remember at most 0.14n
patterns with some probability of error.
But, mathematically,
it's possible to generate a weight
matrix that can actually store many more
than 0.14n patterns.
And ideally,
these patterns should be somewhat
correlated with one one another. If you
want patterns that are completely
uncorrelated with one another, it turns
out that the maximum number of patterns
you can remember is n.
But, if you let the patterns not be
be you know, have some correlation,
you can store more than n patterns,
right? So, how can we actually design a
weight matrix
such that we remember everything that we
want to remember,
and you don't remember anything that you
don't want to remember? Now, if I set
you guys with this homework
and went away,
and I defined it carefully enough in my
write-up, I'm very sure that every one
of you guys would solve it.
Right? So, how would you go about doing
this?
Anyone?
Can we solve this on the board?
There's a bunch of other slides on math,
but I'll skip the math. But this is the
interesting problem, right? How do you
make a network remember just what you
remember and not remember something that
you don't want to remember?
What would you do this? Do
Based on what you know.
Let's work this out.
Right?
How would you go about this problem?
Hm?
Anybody?
Come on, you're seeing your kids. This
has got to be easy.
Right?
You want a hint? How many of you want a
hint?
Raise your hand if you want a hint.
Okay.
What is it you're trying to What What
makes a
pattern that you want to remember
special?
In terms of
formally and math.
Hm?
No, weights. Weights are what you're
trying to estimate. What makes it
special?
What is minimized at these patterns?
>> Energy.
>> Energy, right? So, what is the
characteristic of your patterns?
>> They're all
a minimum.
>> Minima of?
>> Energy.
>> All right. So, I have all of these Y's.
I want minus half
Y transpose W Y.
This should have a minimum
at your target patterns, right?
So, this tell you an idea of how you
would go about designing this network?
Come on, guys. Easy.
You're halfway there, yes?
Gradient descent, lovely. But gradient
What is the objective function?
That thing for I have many patterns I'm
trying to remember.
So, what's it going to be?
Come on.
Mhm?
Continue.
>> So, there's many objective functions for
the
>> No, I have many patterns I'm trying to
remember, right?
So,
how would you do this? Come on.
Mhm?
Yeah?
>> Make a matrix to
remember all the weights we trying to
>> The weights are what you're trying to
estimate, right?
>> It's a square matrix.
>> The weight is a square matrix, right?
What is the actual objective you're
trying to minimize?
You're trying to minimize the energy at
every one of your patterns,
right? Do you need more hints?
Come on, guys. This is very, very easy.
>> I'd like to use like minimize the error.
I'd like the square mean error.
>> What error? I'm telling you exactly what
it is you want to minimize.
>> The gradient.
>> Y such that
minus half
Y transpose W Y
is
minimum at Y, right?
So, if I give you a single Y, what is
the objective you'd minimize?
Energy. If I give you 10 Ys,
>> 10 energies.
>> Mhm?
>> Minimize all of the 10 energies.
>> Minimize Can you say that aloud, please?
>> Minimize all 10 energies.
>> Minimize all 10 energies, right? You're
going to do
summation over all the
patterns you want to remember,
Right? Off, and have the half outside,
Y transpose W
Y.
This is your loss.
Does that make sense?
Should you have thought of it?
Yes, no?
>> Yes.
>> Okay, everybody aloud?
>> Okay. Is that enough?
What is it you don't want to do?
Say that aloud, please.
>> I
remember the things that I don't want to
remember.
>> You don't want to remember the things
that you don't want to remember,
correct? How do you account for that
here?
>> Minus the sum of the things
>> Hm?
>> Minus the sum of the things I don't want
>> Fantastic. So,
see, I just have to give you a hint.
Right? And so, I can just say
Forget about all the hack that Hopfield
went through for that one of my Nobel.
You guys are going to do better, right?
Uh and so, I'm going to say L
equals
summation over
Y that belongs to the set I want to
remember.
And let's call this remember.
Minus half
Y transpose
W Y.
And
I'll put the minus outside.
And then I do a plus.
All the things that I don't want to
remember.
Half of
Y transpose W Y. Is this making sense to
all of you guys?
You don't want to There are things you
want to remember. You want the energy
minimize there.
Things you don't want to remember, you
want to maximize the energy there,
right?
This tends to be a little more little
painful.
Suppose I just did this over all Y.
Do you think it's going to make a
tremendous difference?
Mhm?
>> Probably not.
>> Not really, right? So, because uh
the number of things you want to
remember is really so small, typically.
Hopefully, if you're trying to remember
everything, it's not a memory at all,
right?
So,
I'll skip this, okay?
And I'll skip this poll. Actually, can
somebody
tell me the answer over here? Someone on
Zoom?
Can you give me the answers to this?
>> The first one.
>> The first one?
True.
Second one?
>> False.
>> False. Third one?
>> Third one?
That's false, right?
It's probabilistic, right? It could or
could not remember 0.14 M patterns. We
said that when you don't remember more
than one pattern, there's always a
probability that it won't.
So, that was where Hopfield left it off.
He came up with this algorithm, which is
kind of trivial, and then he proved with
his own math that it doesn't work.
And um
then we go ahead from there. And what
you guys have just done is come up with
a proper decent formula
to do one better than Hopfield.
So, let's try to see how that works,
right?
Uh
I'll skip all of this
fancy math.
Not necessary. Let's get to the
bottom line, right? You want E to be
minimized for all of the patterns you do
want to remember,
and you we E you don't want E to not be
minimized
at any other pattern. Okay.
But then if I have
So,
this is what we want, correct? This is
your loss function.
And
if I use gradient descent,
then it's very easy for me to do this.
I just take the different I just take
the derivative of this guy with respect
to W.
And that's going to give me my
uh
learning rule, right? What is the
derivative of
Y transpose W Y with respect to W?
Anybody remember this?
It's a quadratic.
What is the derivative of A X A X with
respect to A?
Mhm.
If it was scalars, what's it going to
be?
What's the derivative of
you know, X A X?
What's this? Come on, guys. This is
easy.
I'm taking the derivative with respect
to A.
Come on.
>> What happened? X times X?
>> Thank you. Right. Was that so hard?
Eighth grade math or was that 10th
grade? You guys are smart. I'm sure you
finished this before most people grew
their teeth, right? And so, uh yeah.
What's it going to be like in the vector
case?
Is W a scalar or a matrix?
Matrix. So, what would that So, is the
is the derivative going to be a scalar
or a matrix?
>> Matrix.
>> Matrix. So, what do you think it's going
to be?
I've got a vector Y and a vector Y,
right? How do I form a matrix out of it?
Mhm?
Jacobian It's a a right? So,
if I take a vector, the outer product of
a vector with itself is going to be a
matrix.
That thing is going to be the derivative
of that, the two is is going to be
y y transpose.
Right? Same as this, except that you
make sure that the shape remains, right?
And so, here's what we got.
The gradient descent rule just ends up
being
delta w plus summation of y y transpose
for all the target patterns
minus y y transpose for the
things I don't like, right? Now, going
back over here, does this look familiar
at all?
Suppose I had only one target pattern.
What is y y transpose going to be?
Did we Did we just hear about it a few
minutes ago?
What?
>> It'll be one.
>> Is it No, it's a matrix It's a vector,
right? Y's and Y's What's it going to
be?
No, this was the Hebbian learning rule.
The w i j is going to be the ith
component of y times the jth component
of y, correct?
Yes?
So, this is just the Hebbian rule. It
turns out the Hebbian rule that uh John
Hopfield came up with is just half the
formula.
That's why it doesn't work.
What it's doing is it's capturing the
first term, the average of y y
transposes for all the patterns you want
to remember,
but it's ignoring the second term,
the y y transposes for all the patterns
you
don't want to remember, right?
Beautiful, huh? We sort of figured out
why
why the whole
you know, where
Hopfield's rule came from
and why we don't think it should work
and how to fix it, right? Is that making
sense to everybody?
And do you feel that
you came up with this on your own?
You did, right?
You just need You need You just needed
some prompting, right? Is this going to
work?
Yes, now.
>> It should.
>> Okay, it should. So, but are there any
reasons why this could be problematic?
Any reasons? Yeah.
There's a much more practical reason,
right? How many of these patterns exist
that you don't want to remember?
How many exist that you don't want to
remember?
Yeah, can you give me a number?
They're not infinite. If I have n
neurons, how many patterns can you have?
2 raised to n.
Right? And so, you're going to have an
exponential of number of things. So, can
you actually directly apply this rule?
That second term is going to need an
exponential number of summations. This
is This first guy is your heavy and
rule, and if there are some patterns
which are more important than others,
you can present it again and again.
This guy
is a problematic one. Right?
There are an exponential number of these
guys.
Okay?
But do we really need to use all of
them?
This is where the smart engineering
business comes in, and I'm
See I'm here students, so you guys are
going to help me, right?
I have an energy contour
of this kind
for any given W, right?
And now for a current W, so I chose a
random W. If I chose a random W, I get
an energy contour, right?
And say this is a target pattern I want
to remember,
and this is a target pattern I want to
remember.
How do I want to modify the W? What
should I be doing to the energy contour?
Uh yeah.
>> Patterns need to go down in the local
minima.
>> I need the W to go down at those two the
the to be modified such that the energy
goes down at those two locations and up
everywhere else, right? So, do I really
need to be pushing everything up?
Do I need to be pushing all of these
guys up and pulling this one down?
Or is there a smarter way of doing it?
Yeah.
>> Shift the local minima.
>> I can just push these guys up, right?
And pull this down.
At each point I can just pull the local
minimum up and push the target uh push
the local minima up and pull the targets
down.
How do I find the local minima?
Yeah.
Anybody?
>> Use the second derivative and the first
derivative.
>> It's a large matrix and it's again
>> Gradient descent.
>> Gradient Gradient descent? No, this is
an evolutionary process, right? If I
start the network at some point, where's
it going to end up?
Local minimum. So, how do I find the
local minima?
I just run the network. See, she's she's
going to win the next Nobel, right?
See? So, here's what I do.
I'm going to get the both a quadratic.
You get the idea, right? But if they are
the one of a quadratic as we saw, so
it's going to be inverse quadratic.
These are target patterns you want to
pull down.
You want to pull up everything,
but that doesn't make sense.
So, your name?
>> Jenning.
>> Jenning? Okay. So, we're going to do
what Jenning Any does anybody else want
to give me smarter answers than that?
Right?
That's a very good answer, right? That's
that's brilliant because she just
uh short circuited many years of
research.
And so,
what you're going to do, you're not
going to pull up everything. You're
going to find these guys and pull them
up.
And the way you would do it,
right?
How do you identify these guys?
Exactly as she said. I can randomly
initialize the network any odd how,
and let it evolve.
And it's going to fall into these local
minimum.
And so, here is my learning rule,
right? Randomly initialize the network
several times, let it evolve, settle at
a valley. You're going to get a bunch of
valleys.
And then, you're going to use this
formula here. Where is my pointer?
And this is going to be done over your
target patterns.
The second term is going to be done only
over the patterns that were not target
patterns.
The ones that the network evolved into,
right?
Is that a good answer?
Yes, no.
Hm?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, it's a pretty good answer, right?
But, can
are there
What is the challenge with this?
>> Random initializations might not capture
every local
>> Uh let's say Yeah, you're going to
capture some subset, right? You're not
going to capture everything. That's one,
but something more important?
At every gradient descent step,
you're going to have to because changing
the W changes the local minima,
you're going to have to do this entire
business of letting the network evolve
all over again.
Right?
So, yes. It's better than finding an
exponential number of those guys.
And so, the solution that they came up
with was exactly what Jenny explained
suggested.
And uh several papers appeared in
nature. You should try.
And uh this was the technique.
Until we realized that you know, it
doesn't
we can be more efficient.
So, how can we be more efficient? Right,
this randomly initialize doesn't make
sense.
I mean it makes sense
but we can do better.
So, let's go back to this picture.
Suppose I have this.
Right? And these are the only two
patterns I'm trying to remember.
Do I have to push up every local
minimum?
Then?
Which ones do I need to push up?
>> The one between the target patterns.
>> The one between the target patterns. The
one not between but near the target
patterns. Right? If I push this guy, if
I start over here
it's going to go away from it. It's
going to end up here. Right? If I start
over here, it's going to end up here. If
I push these guys up
then I'm guaranteed
that my patterns are stable and and
stationary. You're still going to have
some rubbish far out away. Right?
But remember you're thinking in terms of
content addressable memory. So, I don't
need to pick random locations. It
doesn't make a lot of sense
because
too many of those guys right now. No
offense intended. It's a brilliant idea.
That's what they wrote lots of papers
about.
You can do one up on that by just
picking the patterns close to the
valleys close to your target patterns.
How would you do that?
You know the answer.
>> From the network starting from
>> You start from your target pattern and
let the network evolve. Guys, okay, you
got to
you know
Now, this is an ego thing. Right? You
got
You have to give me the next answer.
Okay.
And so, I can just I don't need to pick
up all of these guys. I just pull these
guys up.
And the way I would do it, I would
initialize the network at these target
patterns, let it evolve
and then pull those things up. So,
initialize the network at valid
memories, let it evolve, it's going to
settle in a valley.
If it's not the target pattern, then
raise it, right? And so, now those guys
on top
these are going to just be Where is my
trident?
This second term is just going going to
be the valleys it decided in. And so,
this changes your stochastic gradient
descent approach framework. Earlier,
what we did was that in each step, you
had to randomly initialize the network a
few times, find the valleys, and pull
them up. Now, you do something more
simple.
Right, initialize the network with each
target pattern
and let it evolve, right? You can
compute this guy for the target pattern
already.
You're going to compute this after it
evolves. And so, when you're doing SGD
at each step, you're going to pull up a
pattern,
compute the first term, let it evolve,
it settles,
then compute the second term, the
difference is going to be a gradient
descent
update. Is that making sense to
everybody?
Aliana?
Okay. You're answering the next
question.
Okay.
Yes.
Uh
Can I do better?
Anyone?
Right. So, that's just my gradient
descent.
Let's find the challenges. You're
already doing pretty well. You know,
right? Jenny's got a goddess like 90% of
the way there.
Let's see the final 10%.
When you evolve, when you're looking at
when you're performing SGD, you're
looking at a target pattern.
You have no idea if you're sliding past
another target pattern to go to a valley
and pulling it up.
Right?
And this happens, right? So, how can you
avoid this?
Anyone?
>> Small learning rate.
>> Small learning No, but it's still a
entire gradient, yes.
>> I don't know, maybe like smaller values
around.
>> Fantastic, right? Okay.
I don't let it evolve for any number of
steps.
I just let it evolve for a small number
of steps. So, what I will do no need to
raise the entire valley, right? Same
thing.
There's no need to
raise every valley in the neighborhood.
You don't need to go to the valley. You
just go close
to the minimum and raise it. And this is
based on the principle that
you really want If I pull this guy down
and push this guy up
it's going to become a broad valley at
this location, which is exactly what we
want. We like broad valleys, right? And
so
starting from the target pattern, let
the network evolve only a few steps.
And now you have a new pattern.
And so, the difference between the outer
products of those two guys
is what is going to be the gradient that
you're updating things with. I skipped
all the text on the slides. I skipped
the math, but did all of this make sense
and do you think you can reproduce it
from the concepts we just learned,
right? I'm not interested in you guys
remembering the math. I want you to
remember exactly what happened and why.
Right. It all started with the
definition of the
energy.
We found that
John Hopfield's
update rule was actually minimizing the
energy at only the target patterns, but
it did not consider what happened at
other locations. We fixed it by saying
we're going to raise everything at other
locations. Thank you, Jenny. And then we
found that we don't need to do it
everywhere, so we said let's take it at
only the local minima. Thank you again.
And we found you don't need to do it
everywhere.
So, we just do it in the neighborhood.
Thank you again. Right?
And so, that's going to
give us a solution, right?
And so, this is
We have time for the fourth poll.
Thank you. Okay. Can you tell me which
statements are right?
Since you're already done.
>> Uh
the
first and second for sure, and then I
think the fourth. I'm not that sure.
>> Hopfield networks can be trained using
gradient descent. We just saw that.
Each gradient step is identical to
Hebbian learning.
Where we learn target patterns and
unlearn non-target patterns.
It's not necessary to update them for
all non-take target patterns.
And each update takes many steps of
computation. Not only takes a finite
number of steps the way we just did it,
right?
And so,
that's where we are.
Hopfield networks, we saw what Hopfield
networks are.
They are loopy networks that thanks to
their loopy behavior end up becoming
content addressable memory.
They can be trained to remember specific
patterns
and not remember the rest of the other
patterns. That's important, right? And a
network that can
uh
the number of patterns they can remember
is order n.
So, it turns out that if you work the
math,
look through the slides, uh if the
weight matrix is not symmetric, if it's
random,
then the expected number of patterns you
can remember is exactly one.
But, if you make the weight matrix
symmetric,
then it turns out that the expected
number of patterns that you can remember
increases exponentially with the with n,
except the exponent is very small. It's
1.06.
So, it's 1.06 raised to n.
And our task is trying to squeeze the
maximum out of this 1.06 raised to n,
which means uh
you know,
you want to come up with approaches
which can remember more than just one or
a small number of patterns.
And so, the way we did it was with we
designed the network
to minimize the energy at target
patterns,
maximize it adjacent to the target
pattern, and things that are very far
away we didn't really care, right?
So, that's where we are.
In the next class, we'll see how this
whole thing becomes a statistical model.
Actually ends up being a generative
model and the genesis of everything
neural network that you do today.
All right?
Any questions?
No? Thank you.